Inventory of the 40th Bomb Group Association records
Hoover Institution Archives
40th Bomb Group Association records
1943-1995
87017
Hoover Institution Archives
17 manuscript boxes, 2 motion picture film reels (6.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, newsletters, memoirs, and audiovisual material, relating to activities of the 40th Bomb Group in the China-Burma-India and Pacific Theaters during World War II, and to subsequent activities of veterans of the group. Includes photocopies of histories of other World War II American bomb groups
40th Bomb Group Association
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1987.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The organization of veterans of the United States Army Air Forces 40th Bomb Group was started in 1980 in order to retain relationships and memories of the 40th Bomb Group's veterans by holding yearly reunions for members.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection relates to activities of the 40th Bomb Group in the China-Burma-India and Pacific Theaters during World War II, and to subsequent activities of veterans of the group. The collection is almost entirely the correspondence of several key members of the association, mostly focused on the organization of annual reunions in the United States after the conclusion of the war and into the 1990s.
The Association also published "War Stories" and "Memories" written by various former members of the 40th about their experiences in the war. This collection contains photographs from the annual reunions after the war as well as material and photographs created during or immediately after the war.
United States Army Air Forces Bomb Group, 40th.; Motion pictures.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Burma.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--East Asia.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.
- "Introduction and Short History of 40th Bomb Group", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Association Newsletters, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1980-1994
  - List of 40th Bomb Group Association correspondences, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - List of 40th Bomb Group Association correspondences, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4-6, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jan-Mar 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Apr-May 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jun-Oct 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Nov-Dec 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Jan-Feb 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mar-Apr 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Aug-Oct 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Nov-Dec 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jan-Feb 1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mar 1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Apr-May 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Jun-Aug 1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sep-Dec 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Jan-Feb 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mar-Apr 1985 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - May-Jun 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Jul-Sep 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Oct-Dec 1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Jan-Feb 1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mar-Apr 1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - May-Jul 1986 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Aug-Sep 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oct-Dec 1986 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Jan 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Feb-Apr 1987 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - May-Jun 1987 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Jul-Aug 1987 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Sep-Oct 1987 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Nov-Dec 1987 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Dec 1987-Feb 1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mar-Apr 1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - May-Jun 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1988 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Jan-Feb 1989 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Mar-May 1989 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Jun-July 1989 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Aug-Oct 1989 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Nov-Dec 1989 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Jan-Mar 1990 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Apr 1990 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - May-Aug 1990 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Sep-Dec 1990 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Jan-Apr 1991 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Jun-Aug 1991 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Sep-Dec 1991 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Jan-Apr 1992 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - May-Aug 1992 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Sep-Dec 1992 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - 1993 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - 1994 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- "Memories from the 40th Bombardment Group,", 1984-1987 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- "40th Bomb Group Association Memories,", 1987-1989 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- "40th Bomb Group Association Memories" bound copy, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- "40th Bomb Group Association Memories,", 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- "40th Bomb Group Association Memories,", 1992-1994 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- "I Wanted Wings" Poem, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
- "B-29 Pilot Memories from the 40th Bombardment Group,", 1987 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Inventory of Harry Chagnon's videotapes, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Early manuscript and publisher commentary on "Eddie Allen" book, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- "Recollections of 40th Bomb Group Tail Gunner Jack Halpern,", 1990-1991 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- "Disaster Over Rangoon,", 1991 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- "Downed Air Crews in Soviet Russia" materials, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- "Personality Sketch of Three 40th Bomb Group Officers" by Marvin Goodwyn, C.O. 45th Squadron, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- "Recollections of T/Sgt Jack Halpern, 40th Bomb Group,", 1994 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- "B-29's on Display,", 1986 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Collected materials pertaining to B-29 Bombers, 1944-1994 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- "B-29 Bibliography" by Denny Pidhayny, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
- "B-29 Bibliography" by Denny Pidhayny, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Photographic histories of Air Force groups, 1944-1947
  - Picture history of the 6th Bombardment Group, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Picture history of the 444th Bombardment Group, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Picture history of the 462nd Bomb Group, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Picture history of the 468th Boombardment Group, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Picture history of the 505th Bombardment Group 313th Wing Air Force, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Picture history of the 9th Bombardment Group 313th Wing Air Force, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Flash reports and wartime documents from Bomber Commands, 1944-1945 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Pictures of the 40th Bombardment Group by Lawrence Eustis, 1944-1946 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- "History of the Fifth Bomber Group,", 1946 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Wartime News materials, 1942-1945 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
- 40th Bomb Group Wartime correspondence, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Wartime news articles, 1943-1945 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Orders and military documents, 1942-1945 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Recollections and wartime diaries, 1944-1986 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- "Van Dorn Hooker Wartime Scrapbook of Drawings,", 1944-1945 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes picture from the China-Burma-India 25th Squadron, 40th Bomb Group
- 40th Bomb Group photographic reconnaissance of bombing targets materials, 1944-1945
  - Anshan and Yawata Attacks, 1944 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Okoyama, Takao, Omura, Malagaon Yards Attacks, 1944 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Malagaon (cont.), Singapore, Rama VI Bridge, 1944-1945 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Rama VI Bridge, Government House Georgetown, Kagi A/D Formosa, Hiro Naval A/C Factory Attacks, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Oshima Naval Oil Storage, Nagoya, Tokyo, Yokohama, Kobe Attacks, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Kawanishi A/C Nauro Plant, Osaka, Toyohashi, Kure Arsenal, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Sumitomo, Okayama, Kure Urban, Takamatsu, Chiba Attacks, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Sendai, Utsonomiya, Numazu, Fukui, Kawanishi Attacks, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Sumitomo, Hachioji, Fukuyama, Hiroshima, Hikari Naval Arsenal Attacks, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Sound recordings, 1943-1990 (Box 16)
  Note
  On three compact sound cassettes.
  - "Ray Carr History" (Tape 1)
  - "Sam Hickey 7-BG History" (Tape 2)
  - "Wayne Covert Bomb. 9th M. E. SR India" (Tape 3)
- Motion picture film
  - "40th Bomb Group" 16mm film (Film shelf Film shelf)
  - "Film Made by Andrew Foti, World War II Film Shot in India," 16mm film (Film shelf Film shelf)